<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon concerning decencie and order in the church Preached at VVood-Church, in the diocesse of Canterburie, April. 30. 1637. By Edward Boughen parson of Wood-Church.</title>
            <author>Boughen, Edward, 1587?-1660?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113532</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848765</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848765</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13878</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16491)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13878)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 626:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon concerning decencie and order in the church Preached at VVood-Church, in the diocesse of Canterburie, April. 30. 1637. By Edward Boughen parson of Wood-Church.</title>
                  <author>Boughen, Edward, 1587?-1660?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. Raworth for I. Cowper, and are to be sold at his shop, at the east end of Saint Pauls Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13878:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON CONCERNING DECENCIE and ORDER in the Church. Preached at VVOOD-CHURCH, in the Dioceſſe of CANTERBURIE, April. 30. 1637. By EDWARD BOUGHEN Parſon of <hi>Wood-Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <bibl>Conſtit. Apoſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Church is the Schoole not of diſorder, but of good (or decent) order.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>I. Raworth</hi> for <hi>I. Cowper,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop, at the Eaſt end of Saint PAVLS Church. 1638.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:13878:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:13878:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1. Cor. 14.40.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat it is the <hi>duty of a Biſhop,</hi> not onely to be carefull, that his flock be trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up in the <hi>faith</hi> and feare of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but that they know, how to <hi>behave</hi> themſelves in the Houſe and Church of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that is, that they not onely pretend <hi>faith,</hi> but that they alſo obſerve <hi>order</hi> and <hi>decency,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> manifeſts not onely in this Chapter, but in the eleventh alſo of this Epiſtle.</p>
            <p>In the 11. Chap. <hi>men</hi> muſt be <hi>uncovered</hi> in the time of <hi>divine ſervice,</hi> verſ. 4. But <hi>women</hi> at that time muſt be <hi>vayled</hi> or <hi>covered,</hi> verſ. 5. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt come to the Lords Table upon a <hi>full ſtomack,</hi> verſ. 21. That we repaire not to the Lords Table but upon due <hi>examination of our ſelves,</hi> verſ. 28. That we <hi>come</hi> not to that <hi>bleſſed Supper</hi> ſtragling, one at this houre, and another at that, but all <hi>together,</hi> verſ. 33. That the Church be not made an houſe to <hi>feaſt</hi> in, to eat and drink in. verſ. 22.34.</p>
            <p>In this Chapter, That <hi>Preaching</hi> be <hi>in a knowne tongue,</hi> verſ. 2. <hi>Prayer</hi> in the like tongue, verſ. 14. That while we are at <hi>Church</hi> we be all <hi>doing one
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:13878:3"/> and the ſame thing,</hi> at one and the ſame time, verſ. 26. not one Praying, another Singing, and a third Prating; to ſay no worſe. <hi>God is not the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of</hi> ſuch <hi>confuſion,</hi> and diſorder, verſ. 33. That <hi>women</hi> be <hi>ſilent in the Church,</hi> verſ. 34. Theres no ſpeaking for them, unleſſe they be asked a queſtion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Preaching</hi> is commendable, and <hi>Tongues</hi> are commendable; and are not <hi>Pſalmes</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> neceſſarily to be uſed in the Houſe of God? And yet <hi>Omnia decenter,</hi> a care of <hi>decency,</hi> and a care of <hi>order</hi> muſt be had in <hi>every one</hi> of theſe.</p>
            <p>Here then is that generall rule for our behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in the Church, whereby <hi>Principales magiſtri,</hi> our chief Rulers ought to ſquare out their <hi>Injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions;</hi> and whereunto <hi>paſsivi diſcipuli,</hi> we that are ſubject to authority, muſt ſubmit our ſelves with all alacrity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Calvin</hi> therefore tells us, That the whole <hi>policy</hi> of the Church, and the whole <hi>duty</hi> of a peaceable Chriſtian, is briefly compriſed in this ſhort <hi>Canon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvi.</hi> in 1. Cor. 14.40.</note> or exhortation: <hi>Haec eſt regula</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ad quam omnia, quae ad externam policiam ſpectant, exigere convenit;</hi> namely, <hi>Let all things be done decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is <hi>Fiant,</hi> a word of action: This word is like an Image of <hi>Iuno's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lucian</hi> de Dea Syria.</note> which I have read of; it lookes this way, and that way, and every way: it hath an eye upon thoſe, that governe, and an eye upon thoſe that ought to be governed; not onely upon the <hi>Law-makers,</hi> but upon the <hi>Law-keepers</hi> too.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Law-makers, Omnia fiant,</hi> Let <hi>all</hi> your
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:13878:3"/> 
               <hi>Lawes,</hi> let <hi>all</hi> your <hi>Canons</hi> bee made according to <hi>decency,</hi> according to <hi>order.</hi> And, bleſſed be God (I ſpeake it from the heart) they have done their parts, they have <hi>done all things decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I would to God, wee were as ready with our <hi>Fiant,</hi> to anſwer their care with our duty; that is, that <hi>All things</hi> were <hi>done</hi> by us, <hi>with that decency and order,</hi> which they have preſcribed.</p>
            <p>I know, it is an eaſier matter to <hi>preſcribe,</hi> then to <hi>performe</hi> a duty: I have therefore alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſhow you, that the duties enjoyned are <hi>eaſie,</hi> and <hi>fit</hi> to be performed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eaſie,</hi> I ſhew by my example. For you know,<note place="margin">The <hi>duties</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned are <hi>eaſie,</hi>
               </note> that I perſwade you to <hi>doe,</hi> to obey no <hi>order,</hi> that is common to me with you, but what I my ſelfe ſtrictly obſerve. And (I hope) that all thoſe, which are not the children of diſobedience, ſee it to be <hi>decent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they are <hi>fit</hi> to be performed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>and</hi> fit to bee performed.</note> I have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted unto you heretofore, by doctrine, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and authority. And now I ſhall endeavour more fully to ſatisfie you in theſe points; that ſo I may ſtirre you up to a cheerefull perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of thoſe duties, which are more ſtrictly exacted now (then heretofore) by the care of our religious and circumſpect Dioceſan and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitan; not without authority from the Lawes both of State and Church, and Gods owne booke, which adviſeth, that <hi>All things be done decently, and in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, here is a <hi>Fiant</hi> for us, wee muſt bee <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> wee muſt obey the Bridegroome and his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:13878:4"/> ſpouſe, that is, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, we are to view the <hi>matter</hi> and the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of this <hi>Fiant,</hi> of theſe our <hi>doings.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>matter</hi> is <hi>univerſall, Omnia fiant, Let</hi> ALL THINGS <hi>be done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>maner</hi> is two-fold. 1. <hi>Omnia</hi> DECENTER, All things muſt bee done DECENTLY. 2. <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> SECVNDVM ORDINEM, They muſt bee all done IN, or ACCORDING TO ORDER.</p>
            <p>And this propoſition is conjunctive, it couples both together, <hi>Decenter</hi> ET <hi>ſecundum ordinem, decently</hi> AND <hi>in order:</hi> one of theſe will not ſerve the turne without the other, <hi>Decency and Order</hi> muſt goe hand in hand.</p>
            <p>The parts are five. 1. <hi>Fiant, Let them be</hi> DONE. 2. <hi>Let</hi> ALL THINGS <hi>be done.</hi> 3. <hi>Let them bee done</hi> DECENTLY. 4. <hi>In</hi> ORDER. 5. <hi>Decently</hi> AND <hi>in order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt will manifeſt, that wee muſt not bee <hi>idle</hi> in the Church of God. The ſecond, that we muſt not be <hi>negligent,</hi> or <hi>ſlacke</hi> in our duties. The third, that wee muſt not behave our ſelves <hi>rudely</hi> in the Church. The fourth, that we muſt not be <hi>diſorderly.</hi> The laſt, that we muſt be alike carefull of <hi>order,</hi> as of <hi>decency,</hi> of <hi>decency</hi> as of <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> of the one as of the other. Begin wee with the <hi>Fiant, Let them be</hi> DONE.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">I FIANT.</note>We finde in Scripture ſeverall duties impoſed upon every one of us in particular: ſome are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us, as wee are the immediate members of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> the other, as we are members of the <hi>Church,</hi> which is the<note n="a" place="margin">Eph. 1.23.</note> 
               <hi>body,</hi> or<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 5.23.32.</note> 
               <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:13878:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Quaedam ut homines, quaedam ut cives agimus;</hi> As it is in the State, as it is in every City or Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ſo is it in the City of God, and Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Some things, we do, or ought to doe, as meere <hi>men</hi> by the light of nature; as namely, we ought to be ſober, harmeleſſe, provident for our ſelves: but as we are <hi>ſubjects</hi> of a Kingdome, there are lawes and ſtatutes of the Kingdome, that require obedience at our hands. And as we are <hi>freemen</hi> of a Corporation, we muſt obſerve the <hi>Orders</hi> ſetled in that Corporation, whereof we be members; whether they be for the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall benefit; or whether they be for <hi>decency</hi> only and <hi>conformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus in like manner, as we are <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> there are <hi>credenda &amp; agenda</hi> for every one of us, <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles</hi> to bee <hi>beleeved,</hi> and <hi>Commandements</hi> to bee <hi>kept.</hi> Theſe are <hi>common to all Chriſtians in generall;</hi> he that will be ſaved, muſt thus <hi>beleeve,</hi> and <hi>doe;</hi> be he of what Nation or Church ſoever. But as we are <hi>members of this,</hi> or that <hi>Nationall Church,</hi> there are (to keepe S. <hi>Pauls</hi> word) <hi>Facienda</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned us, matters of <hi>Order,</hi> and matters of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former two we receive from <hi>Chriſt only;</hi> but for the other, we muſt ſtoope to that <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Church,</hi> wherein we live, wee muſt conforme our ſelves to the <hi>Canons</hi> of that Church; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme <hi>all things</hi> in that <hi>order</hi> and <hi>manner,</hi> which ſhee hath appointed; for ſo reaſon, and S. <hi>Paul</hi> require.</p>
            <p>If I become a member of ſome great mans family, or of any City or Corporation, I muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13878:5"/> not bring in any <hi>new orders</hi> with me, but I muſt obſerve thoſe, which I finde already eſtabliſhed. Yee expect as much from your ſervants in your particular families. And is it fit, that the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of the Church ſhould ſuffer us, to uſe what <hi>new faſhions,</hi> and <hi>phantaſticall orders</hi> we liſt in the houſe of God? All reaſonable men will grant this to be very unreaſonable.</p>
            <p>Yea it hath beene concluded long ſince by thoſe great Reformers under King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixt,<note place="margin">Acts and Mon. in Edw. 6. p. 1193. col. 1.</note> that <hi>The externe Rites and Ceremonies are</hi> APPOINTABLE BY SVPERIOR POVVERS; <hi>in chooſing whereof</hi> WE MVST OBEY THE MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GISTRATES. <hi>And if any man ſhall uſe old</hi> (or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) <hi>Rites, and thereby</hi> DISOBEY <hi>the ſuperior powers, the</hi> DEVOTION <hi>of his Ceremonies is made</hi> NAVGHT <hi>by his</hi> DISOBEDIENCE; <hi>ſo that that, which elſe might be good, by pride and</hi> DISOBEDI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ENCE <hi>is now</hi> MADE NAVGHT. This doctrine in thoſe dayes was held ſo pure, and juſtifiable, that Biſhop <hi>Bonner</hi> was commanded by the Kings Councell to preach it at S. <hi>Pauls Croſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem</note> Indeed fit it is, that the ancient and ſetled <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> bee in force, and finde obedience; for they onely are allowed of by authority, and therefore juſtifiable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiant</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul) Let them be done.</hi> Wee may not then (it ſeemes) bee like ſtockes and ſtones, like the pillars or pues in the Church, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in one poſture; ſomething or other wee muſt be <hi>doing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee muſt be ſometimes <hi>kneeling,</hi> ſometimes <hi>ſtanding,</hi> otherwhiles <hi>bowing, when</hi> and <hi>as</hi> we are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13878:5"/> commanded. We muſt either be <hi>confeſsing</hi> our faith, or our ſinnes, or receiving <hi>abſolution</hi> for our ſinnes. Wee muſt be <hi>praying</hi> with the Prieſt, or <hi>anſwering</hi> to the Prieſt, or diligently obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, what the Prieſt delivers you from God; or <hi>praying</hi> God, to <hi>incline your hearts, to keepe thoſe lawes,</hi> which the Prieſt in Gods behalfe exhorts you to obey. There is no idle time ſpared us in the houſe of God; no time for ſleep, or wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thoughts.</p>
            <p>If any man doubt of the Churches authority in theſe points, the Scripture will cleare theſe doubts: for, doth not S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay plainly,<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.34.</note> 
               <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera, cum venero diſponam, The reſt will I ſet in order, when I come?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither was this authority proper and pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to the Apoſtles; by no meanes: for S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells <hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Euſch. hiſt. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Crete,</hi> that<note n="c" place="margin">Titus 1.5.</note> he had <hi>left him at Crete for this very cauſe, that he might ſet in</hi> ORDER <hi>the things, that were wanting,</hi> ſuch as S. <hi>Paul</hi> had not diſpoſed of, when hee was at <hi>Crete.</hi> So much for the generall.</p>
            <p>In particular, if the Preacher turne ſeducer, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is the Biſhops duty to ſtop his mouth, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11. If an heretick breake forth, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>after the firſt and ſecond admonition</hi> RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>IECT him,<note n="d" place="margin">In this ſenſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is uſed. <hi>Conſtit. Apoſt. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> caſt him out of the Church, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.10. If any man fall into looſe and foule ſinnes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cumomni im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio. <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>rebuke him with</hi> ALL AV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THORITY, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.15.</p>
            <p>If any man grow ſtubborn or refractory <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſignifie</hi> ſo much by Letter, <hi>preſent</hi> him to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Dioceſſe, <hi>that hee may bee</hi> made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13878:6"/> 
               <hi>aſhamed</hi> of his doings. 2. <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> 3.14.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3.</note>If any man <hi>teach diſobedience to Authority,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Ibid. ver. 5.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, keep aloofe from him, have no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him.</p>
            <p>Beſides, as we read of thoſe that <hi>teach well,</hi> ſo we read alſo of thoſe, that <hi>rule well</hi> in the Church, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. But theſe <hi>Rulers</hi> could be no other then <hi>Biſhops,</hi> ſince by them<note n="h" place="margin">Cypr. ep. <hi>27.</hi> n. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Omnis actus Eccleſiae gubernatur,</hi> every action of the Church is guided; ſo Saint <hi>Cyprian.</hi> Indeed manifeſt it is, by all hiſtories ſacred and profane, that in thoſe times (and in ſome hundreths of yeeres after) there were <hi>no Governours in the Church but Biſhops</hi> onely; for<note n="i" place="margin">Cypr. ep. <hi>65.</hi> n. <hi>65</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Apoſtles</hi> themſelves <hi>were Biſhops.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> therefore can intend no other Rulers there beſides Biſhops.</p>
            <p>Since then we are under their authority, let us ſubmit our ſelves to their authority; let us do, what we ſhould do; and conſider, that this Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non is univerſall, <hi>OMNIA fiant,</hi> Let ALL THINGS <hi>be done.</hi> Which is the ſecond part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">II. OMNIA fiant.</note>
               <hi>Let</hi> ALL <hi>things be done:</hi> ALL, that are enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Here is nothing at all left to our diſcretion; nothing may be left undone, when and where we pleaſe.</p>
            <p>It is not for us then to take the Canons upon liking, to obſerve one, and neglect another: we muſt make a <hi>conſcience</hi> of obedience. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</p>
            <p>We may not thinke it enough to <hi>ſtand at the Creed</hi> unleſſe we <hi>ſay it</hi> alſo <hi>with the Miniſter au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. 18.</note> with a loud voyce.</p>
            <p>Nor is it enough for us to <hi>ſtand up</hi> onely <hi>at the Goſpel,</hi> according to the<note n="k" place="margin">Quedam <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none,</hi> quaedam <hi>conſuetudine</hi> obſervanter. <hi>Cod. Afric.</hi> in prin.</note> Churches <hi>cuſtome,</hi> but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13878:6"/> we muſt alſo<note n="l" place="margin">Can. 18.</note> 
               <hi>bow at the name of Ieſus;</hi> not as if we were aſhamed of what we did, but <hi>with due and lowly reverence, as it hath been accuſtomed.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring that our Saviour ſayes flatly, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, of him ſhall the Sonne of man be aſhamed, when he comes in his glory.</hi> St. <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.26.</p>
            <p>Neither is it ſufficient for us to be <hi>bare in time of Divine ſervice,</hi> unleſſe we alſo<note n="m" place="margin">Ibidem</note> 
               <hi>reverently kneele upon our knees,</hi> when the Generall Confeſſion, Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tany, Prayers, and Commandements are read; according as is preſcribed in the book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not doe theſe things, or any of them, negligently or careleſly, as if we cared not, whether we did them, or ſo; the Apoſtle ſayes, they muſt be done <hi>decently.</hi> The third part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">III. DECEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER.</note>
               <hi>Decenter, decently. Decency</hi> ſtands firſt in <hi>order;</hi> and reaſon good; for <hi>decency</hi> makes way for all good <hi>order,</hi> and drawes all wiſe men to be in love with that <hi>order,</hi> which in it ſelfe is <hi>decent,</hi> and <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently</hi> obſerved.</p>
            <p>We are met in the houſe of God, in the houſe of Prayer, to do God ſervice. If we were to wait upon ſome great perſon, we would have a great care of <hi>decency.</hi> And ſhall we not be as carefull, when we are to wait on God, and to do him ſervice? Eſpecially in this Houſe, wherein wee are commanded to<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 96.9.</note> 
               <hi>worſhip the Lord in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core ſancto,</hi> in an holy kind of <hi>decency;</hi> or (as we) in the <hi>beauty of holineſſe.</hi> The reaſon is given ver. 6.<note n="b" place="margin">Decus &amp; mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificentia eſt ante eum. <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </note> HONOVR <hi>and</hi> MAIESTY are before him; and BEAVTY <hi>is in his Sanctuary.</hi> God therefore may not be ſerved (in this place of all other) ſlovenly,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13878:7"/> or diſhonourably. Indeed <hi>Munſter</hi> in his tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhews, how God will be worſhipped,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 96.9.</note> 
               <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curvate vos coram Domino in magnificentia ſanctita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> Bow your ſelves before the Lord in a <hi>magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent</hi> kind of <hi>holines.</hi> As if God would have every one of us to ſtrive to outſtrip one another in the worſhip of God, when we meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Houſe. God would have us ſo; but who doth ſo? Verily we forget the place to be <hi>holy,</hi> and our ſelves to be <hi>ſervants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas we ought ſo to behave our ſelves in this place, that if a ſtranger, or unbeleever ſhould look in upon us (by chance) at our devotions, our reverent and devout demeanor might work upon his underſtanding and affections, and winne him to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> whom we thus ſerve, and reverence.</p>
            <p>What a wonderfull <hi>decency</hi> it is, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves in this place, as in the preſence of God: when every man begins with due obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to God, with a<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 95.6.</note> 
               <hi>Venite adoremus, O come, let us worſhip, and fall downe;</hi> when firſt we <hi>worſhip,</hi> and then <hi>fall downe</hi> upon our knees.</p>
            <p>When the Miniſter, like an Angel of light, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in his white veſtment, behaving himſelfe with that gravity, and reverence, and <hi>decency,</hi> which well befits his calling, and the religious duty he hath in hand.</p>
            <p>When the whole congregation ſhall appeare in the preſence of God as one man, <hi>decently</hi> kneeling, riſing, ſtanding, bowing, praiſing, praying altogether, as occaſion ſhall be offered, and we injoyned, <hi>tanquam unanimes in domo,</hi> like men of one mind and religion in the houſe of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13878:7"/> God; as I have heard it credibly reported of the <hi>Lutherans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how unſeemely is it, to ſee ſome kneele, ſome ſtand, ſome fit, ſome leane upon their el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowes? As if they thought of any thing rather then of God, and his ſervice; as if neceſſity, and not devotion, brought us hither.</p>
            <p>Diſtraction in our behaviour manifeſts diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in our minds, and gives a juſt advantage to the enemies of our Church.</p>
            <p>Now, S. <hi>Pauls</hi> cenſure is, that where there be ſuch <hi>diviſions,</hi> ſuch differences in our behaviour, we <hi>come together</hi> in the Church, <hi>not for the better, but for the</hi> WORSE. 1. Cor. 11.17. And thoſe <hi>diviſions,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> there ſpeakes of, were not in points of faith, but in matters of <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt not therefore fancie a <hi>decencie</hi> to our ſelves, ſuch as we affect, but this <hi>decency</hi> muſt be <hi>ſecundum ordinem, in order,</hi> even <hi>according to</hi> that <hi>order,</hi> which is enjoyned. The fourth part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">IV. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Secundum ordinem, in,</hi> or <hi>according to order.</hi> We have ſeene, how <hi>decency</hi> makes way for <hi>order,</hi> and now we come to ſee, what good this <hi>order</hi> brings with it to the Church of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> This we ſhall the better diſcerne, if wee obſerve (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to S. <hi>Paul</hi>) that where diviſions are in any Congregation, where one man ſerves God in this faſhion, another in that, and a third in a manner different from both, there <hi>hereſie</hi> is at the next doore by. For our Apoſtle hath no ſooner told the <hi>Corinthians</hi> of <hi>diviſions</hi> among them in the Church, 1. Cor. 11.18. but in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:13878:8"/> very next verſe he addes, that<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> 
               <hi>there muſt be he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies.</hi> So ſuddenly doth <hi>diſorder</hi> uſher in <hi>hereſie.</hi> God therefore to prevent <hi>hereſie,</hi> diſcards <hi>diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Hee is not the God of</hi> CONFVSION, <hi>but of peace.</hi> 1. Cor. 14.33. What then have the <hi>ſonnes of God</hi> to doe with <hi>confuſion,</hi> or <hi>diſorder?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where <hi>diſorder</hi> is, there's <hi>confuſion,</hi> where con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, there's <hi>diſsention,</hi> where diſſention, there's <hi>tumult,</hi> and tumult turnes to <hi>ſedition.</hi> Indeed all theſe (if interpreters miſtake not) are contained in that one word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> for which we read <hi>confuſion.</hi> And where theſe are, there can be no <hi>peace,</hi> nor the <hi>God of peace.</hi> For are we not too too apt to laugh and jeere at thoſe, that are not of our owne <hi>cut,</hi> that are not in the Church as <hi>unmannerly</hi> and <hi>diſorderly,</hi> as our ſelves are? From hence ariſeth heart-burning, and hatred, which at laſt breake forth into flat combuſtion.</p>
            <p>But, where <hi>one and the ſame order</hi> is obſerved through out the whole Nationall Church, there is quietneſſe, and peace, and love on every hand; and the God of peace and love is ever with them. Such <hi>order</hi> well beſeemes the Churches of the Saints, and glads the hearts of all good men:<note n="c" place="margin">Coloſ. 2.5.</note> and ſuch <hi>order</hi> as this S. <hi>Paul rejoyced to behold</hi> amongſt the <hi>Coloſsians.</hi> God of his mercy ſettle our hearts to embrace <hi>the orders of this Church,</hi> and to delight therein.</p>
            <p>To keepe us in <hi>order</hi> and <hi>uniformity,</hi> Lawes, and Canons are provided, but not without ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties annexed for the offenders.<note n="d" place="margin">Imperfecta di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur conſtitutio, quae poenam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra facientibus non impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dwode. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. de conſtitut. verbo, ſub poena.</note> Otherwiſe <hi>as good no law, as no penalty.</hi> For, where there is no penalty, authority is but a ſcar-crow, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:13878:8"/> every man may doe, what he pleaſe. And then, ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin. Inſtit. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10. §. 31.</note> 
               <hi>Nunquam futurum eſt, ut</hi> OMNIBVS IDEM <hi>placeat, ſi res velut</hi> IN MEDIO <hi>poſitae ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum arbitrio relictae fuerint.</hi> It can never bee, that one and the SAME ORDER will pleaſe ALL, if ſuch matters be LEFT INDIFFERENT, for every one to uſe, or not uſe at his owne plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Fit therefore it is, that an <hi>order</hi> ſhould bee agreed upon, and obſerved alike by ALL in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Nationall Church. And if <hi>all things</hi> muſt be <hi>done according to order,</hi> then ſurely ſome there are, that have power to appoint and enjoyne <hi>order.</hi> And when <hi>orders</hi> are once agreed upon, and enjoyned, it is not for us to queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be fit or no.</p>
            <p>Wiſe men know,<note n="f" place="margin">Ante legem tam licet quide deliberare; ſed lata lege nemo in ſuo ſenſu abundet; ſed eam admittat, &amp; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem obtemperet. Benig. Milletot. de delicto com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muni, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>lawes muſt be obeyed, not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</hi> Thoſe Governors, that make them, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute them ſufficiently; and know, why they make them, though they doe not alwayes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint us with the reaſons. It is reſolved there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth his Councell, that<note n="g" place="margin">Acts &amp; Mon. K. <hi>Edw</hi> 6 p. 1212. col. 2. In the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections given to Dr. <hi>Hopton</hi> by the Kings Councell, to be delivered to the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> (afterward queene) <hi>Anno</hi> 1549. <hi>Iune</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>The fault is great in any ſubject to diſallow a law of the King, a law of a Realme, by long ſtudy, free diſputation and</hi> VNIFORME DETERMINA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION OF THE WHOLE CLERGIE, <hi>conſulted, debated and</hi> CONCLVDED.</p>
            <p>This is moſt agreeable to our Saviours do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, S. Mat. 23.<note n="h" place="margin">S. Mat. 13.2.3</note> 
               <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees ſit in Moſes chaire.</hi> (in the chaire of the Law-maker, the power is now in their hands) ALL <hi>therefore, whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve, and doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:13878:9"/>
            <p>Neither did our Saviour onely teach this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, but he practiſed it in his owne perſon, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us an example, how to behave our ſelves in the like kind. For our Saviour ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe freely to the <hi>orders of that Church,</hi> wherein he lived; as is to be ſeene by<note n="i" place="margin">S. Ioh. 2.13.</note> his obſerving the feaſt of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and of<note n="k" place="margin">S. Ioh. 10.22.</note> the <hi>Dedication of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">S. Luk. 2.22.</note> When <hi>his mother</hi> had beene <hi>purified,</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was<note n="m" place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>preſented to the Lord;</hi> and<note n="n" place="margin">S. Luk. 2.24.</note> for him <hi>an offering was made</hi> of a paire of Turtle Doves, or two young Pigeons. And which was moſt intollerable,<note n="o" place="margin">S. Luk. 2.21.</note> hee was <hi>circumciſed</hi> the eighth day.</p>
            <p>If I ſhould tell you of the ſevere Lawes in the Primative Church, and thoſe Penalties, and Penances, which were ſtrictly impoſed, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſively undergone by Offenders in thoſe times; it would ſtrike you into an amazement. You could not but wonder at the rigour of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, as alſo at the humility and patience of thoſe Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>But our Church impoſeth no ſuch ſharpe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, it enjoyneth no ſuch rigorous courſes. We complaine of eaſe, we cannot of rigour. And yet how few of us willingly obey theſe eaſie, theſe <hi>decent Orders.</hi> But Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is very ſtrict for them, he will have us to <hi>doe</hi> them, and to <hi>doe</hi> them, as they ſhould be <hi>done,</hi> even <hi>Decenter, &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ordinem, Decently, and in,</hi> or <hi>according to Order.</hi> My laſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">V. Decenter &amp; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem.</note>
               <hi>Decently,</hi> AND <hi>according to Order.</hi> To doe our duties but in one of theſe onely, is to ſubmit our ſelves by halfes; but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will have
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13878:9"/> both. It is not then for us, to judge of <hi>decency;</hi> we muſt hold that to be <hi>decent,</hi> which is <hi>according to order</hi> preſcribed: for both theſe goe together in my Text, and we muſt keep them ſo.</p>
            <p>We may not then conceit a <hi>decency</hi> to our ſelves without <hi>order.</hi> This is to affront the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, and all authority. This is to ſide<note n="a" place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> with <hi>Korah;</hi> and is <hi>nota diſtinctionis,</hi> a ſure token, whereby to diſcerne the Schiſmatically minded from peaceable and <hi>orderly</hi> Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Conſider (good brethren) where there is no <hi>order,</hi> there can be no <hi>decency;</hi> and where there is no <hi>decency,</hi> there is as little <hi>order:</hi> and there can be neither, where every man is left to his owne liberty.</p>
            <p>It is an obſervation of a great learned man, that<note n="b" place="margin">Franc. a victor. Relect. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.</hi> n. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> in the ſtate of innocencie <hi>order</hi> ſhould have beene obſerved: and for that end, if man had continued in that ſtate, there ſhould have beene a <hi>power directive,</hi> though not coercive, to have preſcribed <hi>order. Non enim eſset decora Reſpublica</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſi quilibet</hi> SVO RITV <hi>Deum coleret, etiamſi omnes recte viverent:</hi> for the face of the Church could not be <hi>decent</hi> and comely, if eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould ſerve God <hi>after his owne faſhion,</hi> though all men lived never ſo uprightly.</p>
            <p>And what he ſpeakes, is not without reaſon; for Paradiſe and hell are as different as may be. But in <hi>hell</hi> there <hi>is no order.</hi> Iob 10.22. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Paradiſe there muſt have beene <hi>order.</hi> In heaven alſo there is <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity;</hi> as it is to be ſeene. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="sup">c</hi> In the ninth verſe the <hi>Saints</hi> are <hi>all</hi> clothed<note n="q" place="margin">Revel. 7.9.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:13878:10"/> with <hi>white robes;</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>all ſtand</hi> before the <hi>Lambs throne:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ibidem. v. 10.</note> 
               <hi>all cry</hi> with a <hi>loud voyce;</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>all</hi> uſe <hi>one and the ſame thankeſgiving.</hi> And as it is with the Saints, ſo is it with the Angels, verſ. 11.<note n="g" place="margin">Ibidem. v. 11.</note> They <hi>all ſtand</hi> round about the <hi>throne</hi> together:<note n="h" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> they <hi>all fall downe</hi> before the throne together <hi>on their faces:</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ibidem. v. 12.</note> they <hi>all</hi> uſe <hi>one and the ſame doxologie,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Amen: Bleſsing, and glory, and wiſedome; and thankeſgiving, and honour, and power, and might, be unto our God for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Saints have <hi>white robes,</hi> is <hi>decent;</hi> but that they are <hi>all</hi> clothed with white robes, is <hi>orderly.</hi> That they <hi>ſtand before the throne,</hi> and <hi>fall downe before the throne,</hi> is <hi>decent;</hi> but that they <hi>all ſtand together,</hi> and <hi>all fall downe together,</hi> is <hi>orderly.</hi> That they <hi>cry with a loud voice</hi> is <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent;</hi> that they <hi>all</hi> doe ſo <hi>together,</hi> is <hi>orderly.</hi> That they <hi>praiſe, and glorifie God,</hi> is <hi>ſeemely;</hi> but that they <hi>all</hi> praiſe God in the <hi>ſelfe ſame words,</hi> is <hi>ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ordinem,</hi> moſt <hi>agreeable to order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus (you ſee) they <hi rend="sup">1</hi> 
               <hi>all worſhip together,</hi> 2 after the <hi>ſame manner,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">3</hi> in the <hi>ſame poſture,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">4</hi> the ſelfe <hi>ſame way,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">5</hi> with <hi>robes of one</hi> and the ſame <hi>colour,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">6</hi> and in the ſelfe <hi>ſame words;</hi> not mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering betweene the teeth, <hi rend="sup">7</hi> but with a <hi>loud voice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is not this to give us an example, how we ought to behave our ſelves in the Church of God? ſurely our Church (if you well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) may ſeeme to have ſet this heavenly pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne before her, when ſhee made her Canons and Conſtitutions. Let us then humbly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly ſubmit our ſelves, and <hi>doe all things, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13878:10"/> to</hi> that heavenly <hi>order,</hi> which is injoyned.</p>
            <p>Injoyned? By whom? By them, that have power to injoyne it. And who are they? <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Biſhops. Kings,</hi> Rom. 13. the moſt part of that Chapter tells you ſo. And S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſeconds S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this point. <hi>Submit your ſelves to</hi> EVERY ORDINANCE <hi>of man for the Lords ſake: to the</hi> KING <hi>as</hi> SVPREME, <hi>as</hi> alſo <hi>to them, that are ſent,</hi> or <hi>put in authority by Kings.</hi> 1. S. Pet. 2.13, 14. So then to <hi>Biſhops,</hi> becauſe they are put in authority by Kings; if they had no other claime. But (bleſſed be God) they hold not only by this,<note n="k" place="margin">As touching the <hi>Reverend Ordinaries</hi> of this land, if there be any, that diſlike of their callings, or conceive of the ſame as not grounded upon <hi>Apoſtolicall,</hi> and (for <hi>all the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall parts</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) <hi>upon Divine Right;</hi> I would he were with Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi> The holy Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. c. 3. p. 64.</note> but by an higher tenure,<note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 13 1.</note> ſince <hi>all powers are of God;</hi> from him they have their <hi>ſpirituall Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> what ever it be. S. <hi>Paul</hi> therefore (yee ſee) aſſumes this power to himſelfe, of <hi>ſetting things in order</hi> in the Church, before any Prince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Chriſtian. 1 Cor. 11.34. The like power he acknowledgeth to be in <hi>Titus.</hi> Tit. 1.5. And in <hi>all Biſhops.</hi> Heb. 13.17. Where he commands us, to<note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>obey them, that have the rule over us.</hi> And who are they? Even thoſe,<note n="n" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> who <hi>watch for your ſoules,</hi> and <hi>muſt give an account</hi> for your ſoules.<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin.</hi> in Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe</hi> (ſaith <hi>Calvin) without doubt are the Paſtors of the Church.</hi> And a part of their duty it is, to <hi>put us in mind to be ſubject to Principalities, and Powers, and to obey Magiſtrates.</hi> Tit. 3.1.</p>
            <p>Every private man in his owne family ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, that <hi>good order</hi> ſhould bee kept. And what <hi>order</hi> is that? Such as the Maſter of the houſe preſcribes. For he may in his owne fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily injoyne what <hi>orders,</hi> hee pleaſeth, ſo that they be not repugnant to the Lawes of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13878:11"/> Superiors, or contrary to the plaine word of God.</p>
            <p>And ſhall a Prince or Biſhop be in worſe caſe, then an ordinary houſe-keeper? ſhall not the <hi>Prince</hi> have the ſame power in his owne domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> in his Biſhoprick, that every pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate man hath in his owne family? ſhall it not be lawfull for them, to provide ſuch <hi>orders,</hi> as are <hi>decent;</hi> that may raiſe devotion, and increaſe piety?</p>
            <p>Surely if our Saviour, or his Apoſtles, had injoyned <hi>all orders</hi> in particular, there had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained little or nothing for <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to ſhew their authority in,<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Obedite praepoſitis veſtris,</hi> might have beene ſpared, S. <hi>Paul</hi> needed not command us, to <hi>obey our Rulers,</hi> or Biſhops. For if we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, what God injoynes directly <hi>in terminis</hi> in particular, we <hi>obey</hi> God herein, and not our Governors. But we are commanded to <hi>obey our Governors;</hi> and therefore ſomething is left to their diſpoſing, to their <hi>ordering.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Kings make Lawes, and Biſhops Canons. Thus indeed it was of neceſſity in the beginning of Chriſtianity; Kings made lawes for the State, and Biſhops for the Church; becauſe then there were no Chriſtian Kings either to authorize them to make ſuch lawes; or that would counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance them, when they were made. But after that<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> 
               <hi>Kings became nurſing Fathers to the Church,</hi> Biſhops, in thoſe pious and regular times, made no Canons without the aſſent, and conſent, and confirmation of Chriſtian Kings. And ſuch are our Canons, ſo made, ſo confirmed.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:13878:11"/>
            <p>This is one of thoſe Prerogatives, which<note n="r" place="margin">Reges Iudaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non res mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do civicat domi militiaeque mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rati ſunt, ſed <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionibus</hi> etiam <hi>ſacriſque</hi> &amp; <hi>ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniis</hi> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuerunt. P. Cuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eus de Rep. Heb. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings enjoyed, and uſed in the Book of God. King <hi>David</hi> ordered all things for the Arke, and Tabernacle. 1. Chron. c. 15.16.24. Thus <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> for and in the Temple. 2. Chron. 8.14. And <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did in like manner. 2. Chron. c. 29.30.31.</p>
            <p>And doth not <hi>David</hi> order our behaviour in the Church? <hi>O come, let us</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">1.</hi> 
               <hi>worſhip, and</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">2.</hi> 
               <hi>fall doune, and</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">3.</hi> 
               <hi>kneele before the Lord our maker.</hi> Pſal. 95.6. This charge comes from<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. i3.i4.</note> 
               <hi>a man after Gods owne heart;</hi> and hee that diſobeyes, is not a man after Gods owne heart. It comes from a King, and ſubjects muſt obey. It comes from ſuch a King, whom all good Kings are bound to imitate in his reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious commands: and all religious Chriſtians are bound to obey theſe and the like com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>No ſooner did Kings and Emperours embrace the Chriſtian faith, but they made uſe of this Prerogative. <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour<note n="t" place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſt. M. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> ordained, <hi>what dayes ſhould be kept holydayes.</hi>
               <note n="v" place="margin">Ib. c. 17.</note> Hee appointed <hi>orders for the Church.</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Ib. c. 18.</note> Hee provided a <hi>ſet forme of Common Prayer.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ib. c. 25.</note> Hee <hi>confirmed under his ſeale the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons</hi> made by Biſhops in their ſeverall Councels, that ſo the greateſt of his Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders might not ſleight them.<note n="y" place="margin">Socrates l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; Theod. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Yea the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour himſelfe profeſſeth, that his chiefe care was, that there might be but <hi rend="sup">1.</hi> 
               <hi>one faith,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">2.</hi> 
               <hi>ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere charity,</hi> 
               <hi rend="sup">3.</hi> 
               <hi>Et Conſentiens religionis cultus,</hi> and one manner of religious worſhip throughout his
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13878:12"/> Dominions. And<note n="z" place="margin">Donati vox eſt, <hi>Quid eſt impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratori cum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia.</hi> Optat. l <hi>3.</hi> Sic &amp; Petilianus apud D. Aug. cont. lit. Petil. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>92.</hi>
               </note> I finde not, that any but Schiſmatickes and Heretickes were offended at it.</p>
            <p>That in theſe matters, the Emperour uſed the advice of Biſhops is evident; in that he had<note n="a" place="margin">Euſeb. de vita Conſt. M. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>35.</hi>
               </note> the Biſhops alwayes in his company; that<note n="b" place="margin">Sozom. hiſt. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> he made an Act, that the Decrees of Councels ſhould be unchangeable;<note n="c" place="margin">Ibidem.</note> and that it ſhould be lawfull, to appeale from the civill Magiſtrates to Biſhops; but no appeale from them. I could juſtifie as much for <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> and <hi>Charles the Great;</hi> but I haſten.</p>
            <p>If a <hi>ſet order</hi> were not concluded upon by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; if every man ſhould uſe that behaviour in the Church, that likes him beſt; and if every particular congregation ſhould have that <hi>forme of ſervice,</hi> which they conceit beſt, and might alter it at their pleaſure; Lord! what diverſity ſhould wee have? wee ſhould have every yeere at leaſt <hi>new Service bookes,</hi> as wee have new Almanacks: worke, worke, more worke for the Printers; and as much variety of geſtures, as of faces, in the Church. And then<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>if there come in ſome, that are unlearned, or that are unbeleevers, will they not ſay, that yee are mad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereas if they enter into a mannerly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and behold therein one and the ſame <hi>decency according to order,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ibidem. v. 25.</note> 
               <hi>cadentes in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem adorabunt Deum, they will fall downe on their faces, and worſhip God, profeſsing, that God is in you of a truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember, that<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 15.22.</note> 
               <hi>obedience is better then ſacrifice.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:13878:12"/> True (ſay you) obedience to God is ſo. But obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to our Superiours is obedience to God. For hath not God commanded,<note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Every ſoule to be ſubject to the higher powers?</hi> Hath he not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us to<note n="h" place="margin">1 S. Pet. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every ordinance of man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If wee teach ſervants to obey their Maſters, or children to honour their parents, you like wonderfull well of this doctrine, you ſee it plainely ſet downe in holy Scripture. And are not the other commands as plaine? That we muſt ſubmit to the higher powers <hi>for conſcience ſake.</hi> Rom. 13.5. <hi>For the Lords ſake.</hi> 1. S. Pet. 2.13. <hi>As unto Chriſt.</hi> Eph. 6.5. Surely (ſaith <hi>Primaſius,</hi> S. <hi>Auſtines</hi> Scholer)<note n="l" place="margin">Primaſ. in <hi>Eph. 6.</hi> In his quae ſunt commiſſa homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num poteſtati, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>runt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Dei Tho. <hi>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae.</hi> q <hi>100. &amp; 3 <hi rend="sup">m</hi>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſto facitis, quicquid propter Chriſtum hominibus exhibetis;</hi> yee do <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſervice, when yee obey your ſuperiors for <hi>Chriſts</hi> ſake.</p>
            <p>So then in obeying our Biſhops and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors, we obey<note n="k" place="margin">1 S. Pet. 2.25.</note> that <hi>great Biſhop of our ſoules,</hi> who hath commanded us to<note n="l" place="margin">Heb 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to them, that have the rule over us.</hi> And if we do not our duty to them, that are ſet over us, with what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can we expect obedience from thoſe, that are under our government? Our Saviours rule is,<note n="m" place="margin">S. Mat. 7.12.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever yee would, that men ſhould doe to you, do yee even ſo to them.</hi> Obey then, that yee may bee obeyed; <hi>obey heartily,</hi> that yee may be obeyed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly: the <hi>ſervants of Chriſt,</hi> doe ſo, they <hi>obey from the heart.</hi> Eph. 6.6.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that as your children are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to obey you, ſo you are commanded to obey your Governours. But your children are
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13878:13"/> commanded to obey you in <hi>all things.</hi> Col. 3.20. And ſhall you obey the Fathers of the Church in what you liſt? ſurely where the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath made no limitation, it is not for us to make any.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls upon us in generall termes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out limitation, to<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>obey,</hi> to <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to our Rulers, that watch for our ſoules, and muſt give an account for our ſoules.</hi> And gives this reaſon for it;<note n="o" place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi>that ſo they may give up their account with ioy, and not with griefe; for that is unprofitable for you.</hi> Unprofitable it is indeed for <hi>you,</hi> if <hi>Calvin</hi> ſay right; for thus he writes.<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Calvin in</hi> Heb. 13.17.</note> 
               <hi>Significat nos ſine propriae ſalutis iactura, non fore Paſtoribus moleſtos, vel immorigeros.</hi> The Apoſtle acquaints us, that we cannot be offenſive, or undutifull to our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, or Biſhops, without the loſſe of our owne ſalvation. And then he addes;<note n="q" place="margin">Calvin. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>Quum vix deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quiſque hoc cogitet, hinc apparet, quantus vulgo ſit ſalutis neglectus;</hi> ſince there is ſcarce one of ten, that takes this into conſideration, it is too too evident, that there is a generall neglect of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation amongſt us.</p>
            <p>But, it may bee, you are doubtfull, whether that, which is commanded, be lawfull or no. If ſo, then muſt you ſeek for a reſolution from per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons worthy to bee credited in this caſe. And <hi>Calvin</hi> tells us,<note n="r" place="margin">Calvin. Ib.</note> that it is neceſſarily required, <hi>ut plebs</hi> FIDEM <hi>ac ſimul reverentiam Paſtoribus habeat,</hi> that the people BELEEVE and reverence their Paſtors. Indeed who ſo fit to be truſted, as he that is truſted with your ſoules, and muſt account to God for them? If the Parſon or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13878:13"/> cannot ſatisfie the parties doubting, they are then<note n="ſ" place="margin">Preface be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the book of Common prayer.</note> to <hi>reſort to the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe. And if the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe be in doubt,</hi> he is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed <hi>by the Archbiſhop;</hi> and to reſt upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution. Thus wee are taught by the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and this is a ſafe and warrantable courſe.</p>
            <p>If you obey, and truſt them, (though the <hi>caſe</hi> be <hi>queſtionable</hi>) you may juſtifie your obedience<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 13.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by this, and the like texts of Scripture. But if you hearken to any other, that have not the charge of your ſoules, and diſobey them, to whom the cure of your ſoules is committed by your mother the Church,<note n="o" place="margin">Ib.</note> 
               <hi rend="sup">u</hi> the <hi>griefe</hi> will bee your rulers, but the <hi>diſcommodity</hi> yours. <hi>Hoc enim non expedit vobis</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) for this is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable for you.</p>
            <p>It is not for us then to queſtion their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, or to deliberate upon them; we muſt <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue</hi> our Governors, and reverently <hi>obey</hi> them, when they command nothing, that is expreſly contrary to the word or honour of God. S. <hi>Paul</hi> requires <hi>obedience,</hi> not examination; <hi>ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> not conſultation.</p>
            <p>To this adde the <hi>oath of the Churchwardens;</hi> they cannot avoid preſenting thoſe, that obſerve not the <hi>orders</hi> of the Church without manifeſt <hi>perjury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider the warning given them at the <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> namely, that if they preſent not truly and ſincerely, according to the Articles, they are lia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>High Commiſsion,</hi> and upon juſt proofe to be <hi>cenſured</hi> for perjury.</p>
            <p>Pity the <hi>danger,</hi> that you are like to draw up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13878:14"/> your owne heads, or the heads of your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and conforme your ſelves.</p>
            <p>Our Dioceſan deſires rather to amend us, then to cenſure us; and hence it is, that time is given us to redreſſe, what is amiſſe.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>diſobedience</hi> are recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned amongſt thoſe ſinnes, whereinto they uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fall, whom God hath given over to a repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate ſenſe. Rom. 1.28.30.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that to <hi>walke after the fleſh, and to deſpiſe government,</hi> are joyned together. 2. S. Pet. 2.10. Yea (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>)<note n="w" place="margin">Calvin. in ep. B. Iudae. v. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> theſe two are almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable, <hi>ut qui projecti ſunt ad nequitiam,</hi> OMNEM ORDINEM <hi>abolitum eſse cupiant;</hi> that they who have given themſelves over to work wickednes, have alwayes a ſtitch againſt <hi>order,</hi> and would faine have it utterly defaced. And if<note n="x" place="margin">Haec duo ſemper ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c coniuncta ſunt. Calvin. Ib.</note> 
               <hi>theſe two be almoſt inſeparable,</hi> then ſurely they, that are ſuch enemies to order (in <hi>Calvins</hi> judgement) are <hi>projecti ad nequitiam,</hi> lewd, diſſolute perſons. A blemiſh not to be waſhed off, without ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves to <hi>order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider, that REBELLION <hi>is as the ſinne of</hi> WITCHCRAFT, <hi>and</hi> STVBBORNNESSE <hi>as</hi> IDO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LATRY. 1. Sam. 15.23.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that when <hi>falſe teachers,</hi> prophane and blaſphemous ſeducers are decypher'd by the Apoſtles, one of their markes is, that they are <hi>audaces, ſibi placentes, bold, preſumptuous, ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willed men,</hi> DESPISERS OF GOVERNMENT. 2. S. Pet. 2.10. Such as DESPISE GOVERNMENT, <hi>and ſpeak evill of authority.</hi> S. Iude 8.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that they, who miſlead you, are diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13878:14"/> ambitious men, ſuch as <hi>Korah, Nolentes obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dire, quod nequeant imperare,</hi> that cannot indure to obey, becauſe they cannot get into a Rochet.</p>
            <p>Conſider, that thoſe, who ſpeak againſt autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, are undeſerving, ignorant, unlearned men; <hi>Proud, knowing nothing.</hi> So S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. <hi>In his, quae ignorant, blaſphemantes,</hi> ſpeaking evill of thoſe things <hi>they</hi> UNDERSTAND NOT. So S. <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſecond Epiſtle 2.12. And S. <hi>Iude</hi> ſayes the ſame. v. 10. Nay, if <hi>Beza</hi> be not miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken in his tranſlation, they are no better then mad; <hi>Inſanientes circa quaeſtiones ac pugnas de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.4. growing ſtarke <hi>mad</hi> about queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and quarrells concerning words. As if like <hi>mad men,</hi> they left the apple, and fell together by the eares about the ſhadow.</p>
            <p>Obſerve, what ſentence is already paſſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe ſelfwilled, ſtubborne, diſobedient per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. In the Law,<note n="y" place="margin">Deut. 17.8.9.12</note> 
               <hi>The man, that will not (in matters of controverſie) hearken unto the Prieſt, that</hi> IN THOSE DAYES <hi>ſtandeth to miniſter</hi> IN THAT PLACE <hi>before the Lord, that man ſhall die.</hi> In the Goſpel;<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 13.2.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever reſiſteth the power, reſiſteth the ordinance of God; and they that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves</hi> DAMNATION: <hi>damnation</hi> at leaſt of that which is commanded to obey, and that's the <hi>Soule, Rom.</hi> 13.1. S. <hi>Iude</hi> therefore ſaith plainly, that <hi>to theſe is reſerved the blackneſſe of darknes for ever,</hi> S. <hi>Iude v.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>Look upon <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> they mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> Prince, and Prieſt; and they ſuddenly <hi>went downe alive into the pit of hell. Num.</hi> 16.33.<note place="margin">Tertul.</note> 
               <hi>Hoc vero erat futuri judicij prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicium;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:13878:15"/> this doome is a fore-runner of the day of Doome, and a true Preſident of that ſentence, which ſhall paſſe upon diſobedient perſons in that dreadfull day: that ſo all thoſe, that read it, or heare it read, may take warning by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and avoyd the wrath to come.</p>
            <p>God of his mercy grant, that all of us may gaine wiſdome by their loſſe; that with all ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity we may <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to the higher powers,</hi> that we may <hi>do all things</hi> in the Church <hi>decently and according to order:</hi> that ſo we may paſſe from Church to Church, from this Church militant to that triumphant, through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our Saviour, to whom, with the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> three perſons and one God, be aſcribed all honour, and glory, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur haec concio.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN OLIVER. Reverendiſſimo in Chriſto Patri Domino, Domino Arch: Cant. <hi>Capell. Dom.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Vbi metus in Deum, ibi gravitas honeſta, &amp; diligentia ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonita, &amp; cura ſollicita, &amp; adlectio explorata, &amp; communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catio deliberata, promotio emerita, &amp; ſubjectio religioſa, &amp; ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritio devota, &amp; proceſſio modeſta, &amp; eccleſia unita, &amp; Dei omnia.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Tertull.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <pb facs="tcp:13878:15"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
